As for this marriage
婚姻は
It mainly depends on fate
縁次第。
Have that girl called
まず
Wan'er
婉児の生年月日を
Have her birth characters
礼部へ送り
Sent to the Ministry of Rites for calculation
相性を占わせよ。
To see if they match
その結果を見て判断するがよい。
Thank you, Your Majesty, thank you, Father
陛下に御礼申し上げます。 父上に御礼申し上げます。
Enough
よかろう
All dismissed
これにて退きたまえ。
This marriage
この婚約は
Was requested before all the court officials
朝堂の前で持ち上げられたものだ。
Once it's settled
一度決まれば
It means
陛下が
Your Majesty has tacitly approved
寧王と陳家の結びつきを
Prince of Ning and the Chen family further bound together
事実上容認したことになる。
Once they gain momentum
勢いづけば
Those who are watching
様子見の者も次第に
Will gradually align with Prince of Ning
寧王へ帰服するであろう。
Your subject has also learned
臣、さらに聞き及んだ。
General Zu Kun from the north
北方の祖坤（そ こん）将軍が
Is about to return to court to report
まもなく帰還し奏上の予定あり。
It's said
すでに先遣部隊は
The vanguard troops
いくばくか郊外に
Have already camped outside the city
駐営したとのこと。
The Zu family
祖家は
Has always been neutral
これまで中立を貫いてきたが
If
もし
At this time
今この時に
They are swayed
風向きが変われば
Then
それは
It would be terrible
大変な事態となる。
Though the marriage is small
この婚約は小事にあらず
Its implications are great
関わりは深し。
Your Majesty ordered the Ministry of Rites to check compatibility
陛下が礼部に命じて相性を占わせたのも
Likely wants to reconsider
深慮あればこそだろう。
Your Highness
殿下
We must find a way
この婚約を何としても
To ruin this marriage
破談になさる策をお考えあれ。
I understand
心得た。
This old minister
臣
Will visit various parties again
諸方に出向き
And think of other solutions
別の策を講じてまいります。
Mother
母上
Your son has made many arrangements
児臣がいくつか手配を整えております。
Your son Sikong Yao
児、司空耀
Pays respects to Mother
母上にお目通りを願います。
Yao'er is here
耀よ来たか
Second brother
長弟
Quick
さあ
Quick, let Yao'er come in
さあ、入っておいで。
Elder brother is here too
兄上もおられますか？
Second brother
長弟よ、
You
いつ以来
Haven't visited Mother in so long
母上のもとへ参らぬか。
Hurry and apologize to Mother
さあ
By kowtowing
膝ついて詫びよ。
Mother
母上
Your son is not in the palace
宮中に不在がちで
And hasn't visited often
見舞いもままならず
Please forgive me, Mother
どうかお許しを。
Alright, alright
よいよい
That you came to see me
来てくれただけで
Makes me very happy
嬉しいわ。
Today is truly a joyous day
今日はめでたい日じゃ。
My Zheng'er
正児も
And Yao'er
耀児も
Have both come to visit me
揃って顔を見せてくれた。
Xiaoqing
小青
Go get the pastry boxes
先日作った菓子箱を
I made the other day
持ってきておくれ。
What's wrong?
どうした？
Your Majesty
皇后様
You previously gave the pastries to us servants
先お菓子を奴婢たちに下賜されたゆえ、
Now only one remains
今は残りがひとつだけでございます……
Oh, my memory
我ながら忘れっぽいものよ。
Making them now
今さら作るにも
Is too late
間に合わぬな……